<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Us Politics on Jordan Holliday</title>
    <link>/categories/us-politics/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Us Politics on Jordan Holliday</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/us-politics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>10 Thoughts On &#39;North Carolina Is No Longer A Democracy&#39;</title>
      <link>/2017/04/02/10-thoughts-on-north-carolina-is-no-longer-a-democracy/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2017 13:16:28 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/02/10-thoughts-on-north-carolina-is-no-longer-a-democracy/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Three months after it was published, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.newsobserver.com/opinion/op-ed/article122593759.html&#34;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt; by UNC  professor Andrew Reynolds is still getting re-tweeted into my timeline. It is a bad article and I’m disappointed to see such shoddy work coming from a North Carolinian (albeit a &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrew_Reynolds_(political_scientist)&#34;&gt;non-native&lt;/a&gt;) employed by North Carolina’s flagship university. In the interest of making amends for my fair state, here are 10 thoughts on why the article should be retracted and replaced by a sincere apology:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;democracy-is-not-quantifiable&#34;&gt;Democracy is not quantifiable&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is based on a report from the “””Electoral Integrity Project””” (EIP) which scores each state’s democracy on a 1-100 scale. (Reynolds sits on the EIP board). This is a quixotic exercise given that the nature of a democracy has been debated for millenniums, with no consensus yet reached. That Reynolds and the other professors behind this report are blithely scoring democracies on a 100-point scale, with no mention made of the vagaries involved in specifying just what a democracy is, raises a red flag to put it mildly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;it-s-just-a-survey&#34;&gt;It’s just a survey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reynolds’ op-ed gives the impression that he and his collaborators created a rubric for democratic processes, then carefully weighed North Carolina’s system and found it wanting. They did not! Actually, the EIP sends out surveys to political science professors across the country. The surveys have questions about things like voting laws and press freedom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing wrong with surveys, but one survey such as this does not provide the basis for declaring North Carolina a failed democracy. And where does the delineation between “democratic” and “undemocratic” come from? It is a figment of Reynolds’ imagination. The survey did not ask respondents if their states were democracies. Had I participated, I would resent Reynolds going to the press with such an extreme conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;and-it-s-a-bad-survey&#34;&gt;And it’s a bad survey&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The survey asks respondents to agree or disagree with statements like “Votes were counted fairly” and “Some ineligible electors were registered.” Are poli sci professors privy to some special insights that allow them to assess these things more knowledgeably than anyone else? Did they oversee the vote counting? Audit the voter rolls? No. Nevertheless, their responses to these questions are counted for/against a state’s “””index of electoral integrity”””.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;north-carolina-ranked-okay&#34;&gt;North Carolina ranked okay&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When EIP used the survey results to rank the states by electoral integrity, NC came in 37th: ahead of 11 states, tied with two, and within a few points of 10 more. This goes unmentioned in Reynolds’ article. If North Carolina is not a democracy, then neither are broad swaths of the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-rankings-are-absurd-anyway&#34;&gt;The rankings are absurd anyway&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if you accept that ranking states by how democratic they are is a reasonable thing to do, this is a bad ranking. Top-ranked Vermont had four professors respond to the survey. Second-place Idaho had five responses, third-place New Hampshire had five, and last place Arizona had six. Alaska, Delaware, New Mexico, Utah, West Virginia, and both Dakotas had three or fewer responses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These numbers are not included in Reynolds’ article, nor anywhere on EIP’s website, but instead buried in the raw data, presumably because they are woefully insufficient to support the conclusions Reynolds et al. draw.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;north-carolina-did-well-on-the-most-important-question&#34;&gt;North Carolina did well on the most important question&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The EIP doesn’t ask respondents if their state is a democracy, but it DOES ask them to rate their state’s electoral integrity on a 1–10 scale, and to do the same for the US generally. On average, NC received a 7.25 / 10. That looks substantially higher than the 58 / 100 electoral integrity index that the EIP calculated for NC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also of interest: 17 of North Carolina’s 29 respondents rated the state’s electoral integrity on par with or higher than the integrity of US elections generally. Granted I am not a political science professor but that seems like a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;north-carolina-scored-pretty-well-on-the-eip-s-own-scale&#34;&gt;North Carolina scored pretty well on the EIP’s own scale&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to EIP, states that score 50-60 on their hundred point scale have “moderate” electoral integrity. Those that score above 60 have “high” integrity. North Carolina scored a 58.2, which is on the border of moderate and high, and in fact the upper bound of the confidence interval was a 61.8, which would put the state in the high integrity band. This again was not mentioned in Reynolds’ op-ed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;expertise-isn-t-everything&#34;&gt;Expertise isn’t everything&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the issues with the EIP survey and how its results were presented, I want to discuss the topic of expertise generally. Expertise can only get you so far. To cite a recent example, the combined expertise of everyone on Hillary Clinton’s campaign payroll couldn’t beat the buffoon Donald Trump. And of course, none of the experts at the NYTimes, 538, and the &lt;a href=&#34;http://election.princeton.edu/&#34;&gt;Princeton Election Consortium&lt;/a&gt; predicted that outcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that there are things which are, at least for now, beyond the reach of expertise. Measuring precisely how democratic, or not, a state may be, is one such thing. And people like UNC professor Andrew Reynolds, who claim to be experts, should apply their expertise with humility and in measured ways. Declaring you have empirically determined that North Carolina is “no longer… a functioning democracy” is the opposite of that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;the-moral-dimension-of-this-article&#34;&gt;The moral dimension of this article&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did UNC professor Andrew Reynolds fail to uphold his moral obligation as an educator and semi-public figure? I don’t want to lob insults. I don’t know Reynolds and he may be a fine person. But in this instance, Reynolds acted deceptively by withholding such facts as:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;his findings were based on a survey&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;on that survey, North Carolina outscored a number of other US states&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;when asked to rate North Carolina’s electoral integrity on a 1–10 scale, a significant majority of respondents rated it highly (7 / 10 or better)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, when an interviewer from GQ gently &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.gq.com/story/north-carolina-andrew-reynolds-political-science-interview&#34;&gt;pressed Reynolds on the EIP’s methodology&lt;/a&gt;, Reynolds wouldn’t defend the survey and even distanced himself from it, saying “the EIP—which I’m not involved in running, I was just involved in its founding—the EIP is not perfect.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If that’s how he feels, why was he citing the EIP as gospel in his original article? Why didn’t the first article mention the EIP’s flaws? Reynolds concealing his misgivings about the EIP while using it to condemn North Carolina’s democracy is, to me, also deceptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;poor-scholarship-in-slick-packaging&#34;&gt;Poor scholarship in slick packaging&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s really offensive part is that the EIP (which Reynolds may not run but certainly helped publicize) distills its results into a simplistic ranking—effectively a prefab listicle—which is obviously going to garner press attention. The ranking strips the raw data of its complexity, making it easily digestible for all and sundry. When I first saw Reynolds&amp;rsquo; article, I suspected it was bullshit from the word go and confirmed that by looking at the data. Realistically, most people won’t bother to do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most people will read the EIP report, or Reynolds’ article, and leave thinking that North Carolina actually isn’t a democracy, as if there is a global registry of democracies that gets updated each election cycle. That is a conclusion that is somewhere between “highly suspect” and “demonstrably false,” and yet UNC professor Andrew Reynolds is peddling it to the general public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to belabor the point but deliberately misleading the public is the opposite of what UNC professors are hired to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;bonus-thought-what-s-to-be-done&#34;&gt;Bonus thought: What’s to be done?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me conclude by saying I do not think Reynolds should be fired for this. He probably couldn’t be anyway, tenure being what it is. My opinion is that a public reprimand by UNC and an apology from Reynolds would fit the crime &lt;em&gt;and&lt;/em&gt; discourage others in his position from pulling such deceptive, attention-grubbing stunts in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the interest of fairness, I will email Reynolds to see if he cares to respond in this space.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>