<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chicago on Jordan Holliday</title>
    <link>/categories/chicago/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Chicago on Jordan Holliday</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/chicago/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Captain&#39;s Hard Time Dining&#39;</title>
      <link>/2016/12/17/captains-hard-time-dining/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2016 20:37:49 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2016/12/17/captains-hard-time-dining/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Captain’s Hard Time Dining does not cater to those with hang-ups about food sanitation. The paper napkin is likely to be the one piece of your place setting not encrusted with food from previous diners, but if you’re willing to call such oversights “charming” rather than “health code violations,” there’s something special in store. While the offerings are mostly standard—eggs and sausage for breakfast, sandwiches for lunch, basic cuts of chicken and beef for dinner—Captain’s nonetheless operates at the outermost edge of the greasy spoon category, pressing the limits of what’s acceptable to fry, butter, or bread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sides of supposedly “fresh” broccoli and other greens invariably arrive sopping with butter and oil, so instead of beating around the bush, just order the “fried and battered vegetables.” Breads, whether biscuits, pancakes, or rolls, come so thoroughly pre-buttered you’ll want to wring them out. Fried meats aren’t simply fried: They’re “butter fried.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the Captain’s estimation, no dish is so refined that it wouldn’t benefit from a slice of bacon, a side of ranch, or a few onion rings—and mostly, he’s right. True, eat here regularly and you’ll follow up the freshman 15 with the sophomore coronary, but as an occasional treat, there’s no topping the delicious excess of Captain’s Hard Time Dining.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Originally published in the &lt;/em&gt;Chicago Maroon&lt;em&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>