<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Supreme Court on Jordan Holliday</title>
    <link>/categories/supreme-court/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Supreme Court on Jordan Holliday</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <atom:link href="/categories/supreme-court/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Did Senate Republicans Steal Obama&#39;s Nomination?</title>
      <link>/2017/04/11/did-senate-republicans-steal-obamas-nomination/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Apr 2017 08:51:26 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/04/11/did-senate-republicans-steal-obamas-nomination/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Keeping with my preference to stay a step behind the news cycle, I’d like to discuss the claim that Senate Republicans stole Barack Obama’s Supreme Court nomination and held it hostage for a year, before gifting it to President Donald Trump.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This notion, that the Mitch McConnell and co. literally “stole” the nomination, is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/24/opinion/sunday/the-stolen-supreme-court-seat.html&#34;&gt;favorite&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/24/opinion/sunday/the-stolen-supreme-court-seat.html&#34;&gt;talking&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/04/04/opinion/the-supreme-court-as-partisan-tool.html&#34;&gt;point&lt;/a&gt; of the NYT editorial board and similarly-minded folks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways this might be true. The first is if the Senate has a duty to confirm anybody the President nominates. No one believes this. Article II of the Constitution is unambiguous that lifetime judicial appointments require the “Advice and Consent of the Senate….” And Senate Democrats’ recent treatment of Neil Gorsuch would be in serious breach of their duty to rubber-stamp any Presidential nominee, if such a duty existed. But it doesn’t.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a second way you could argue Republicans stole the nomination: If you believe they would not have considered &lt;strong&gt;any&lt;/strong&gt; Obama appointee, you might say they stole the seat by denying Obama his constitutional right to attempt to fill a Supreme Court vacancy. And in fact the NYT editorial board said as much in their &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nytimes.com/2016/12/24/opinion/sunday/the-stolen-supreme-court-seat.html&#34;&gt;December 24 editorial&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[The seat] was stolen by top Senate Republicans, who broke with longstanding tradition and refused to consider any nominee Mr. Obama might send them…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Any&lt;/strong&gt; nominee? Here’s a thought experiment: If Obama had nominated Gorsuch instead of Garland, would the Senate have confirmed him? Of course. Supposing McConnell liked Obama’s nominee, he would have been crazy to delay confirmation hearings till after the November elections, when Hillary Clinton might have been president, Democrats might have controlled the Senate, or both.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When McConnell announced he wouldn’t consider an Obama nominee, behind that statement was an (ultimately correct) assumption that Obama would never nominate anybody who Senate Republicans would consent to. If Obama believed it was vital that the Supreme Court have nine justices at all times, there are plenty of conservative judges who would have made it through the Senate. He had a year to withdraw Garland’s nomination and nominate any one of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obama didn’t do that. As de facto leader of the Democratic Party, he decided Democrats were better off taking their chances  under the next president. The delay in appointing a new justice was as much a result of Obama’s political calculations as of Mitch McConnell’s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Given that Obama and McConnell in essence agreed to punt on the appointment process, why would the NYT editorial board place the blame exclusively on McConnell and the Republicans? Is it because they are so partisan, they are willing to set aside facts when writing their editorials? And why doesn’t Editor-in-Chief Dean Baquet step in to insist that his paper’s editorials consist of something other than the most mendacious propaganda?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are clarifying questions to bear in mind when considering our paper-of-record’s output.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>